[Music]
hello everyone uh welcome to Dynamics
365 business Central launch event my
name is Sandy vinaro I'm a principal
product manager for a business Central
and today I would like to show what's
new in data verse and Dynamics 365 app
integration part two uh as you probably
noticed already part one has been
presented by my colleague Ivan kage and
this is actually a a buildup to that uh
to that
session so the agenda for today's
session is like first I will tell you
the different mission for uh data verse
integration and for Dynamics City 5 app
integration and then I will um I will
talk about the complimentary app or
system interaction that form the fabric
of data verse integration and what are
the key Improvement for this uh
complimentary app interaction that we
plan for this release and one of this
Improvement is actually a major one that
have been requested by many uh partners
and customer which is power page support
via virtual tables and at the end we I
will show you the demo of all this
Improvement all right let's start with
the
mission first the mission for data verse
integration is to offer extensive Fabric
or tools to integrate Dynamics 3 city5
business Central online with other first
and thirdparty business app so not only
for other Dynamics uh business app but
also for other third-party Partners
business app that's run on dataverse
promoting Better Together scenarios
through wider and deeper interaction
with business Central and those apps
what is extensive means extensive means
we want to cover all type of app or
system instructions such as replication
or synchronization or what we used to
call we still calling data sync
virtualization or virtual
tables uh change notification or what we
call data cut events uh data created
updated or deleted events action
notification or what we call business
events right better togethers means
business Central and all those first and
third party business apps should be
integrated in such a way that they
enhance each other fulfilling the
proverbial 1 + 1 equal 3 when used
together in complex business processes
for example a business process that uh
often um uh used with this integration
are lead opportunity quot or order to
cash and wider and deeper means the
integration should increase the breadth
and depth of the interaction
respectively leveraging more and more
types and degrees of interaction between
B Central and those apps such that the
fabric of inter integration are well
intertwined together and increase the
stickiness of those apps all right now
the emission for Dynamics 35 app
integration is actually build up on the
data verse integration Mission
essentially to implement the optimal
approach to integrate Miss Center online
with first party Dynamics 365 apps using
the fabric and tools of data verse
integration that I mentioned before
the optimal means we want to achieve
maximum business impact with minimal
integration effort prioritizing in
demand apps complementary to Business
Center for example we have started
integrating with the dynamic 365 sales
and we are considering to integrate next
the field service and customer service
and marketing Etc so we we want to
enable natural business process hand
over such that like for example uh when
you're dealing with code you should be
doing doing um processing code using
celles and then when you're dealing with
invoice you hand over to business
Central so you make sure that um uh this
um natural Handover avoid functionality
overlap whenever possible within those
apps so let me talk about the
complementary app interaction that form
the fabric of data verse integration let
me just uh give you a review first the
data sync that actually replicate data
changes whenever data is created updated
deleted between overlapping tables in
business Central and data verse for
example in this picture the overlapping
tables are account table native account
table in datae with vendor and customer
table in business Central so you can
actually SN those uh those tables
together using data sync right the
second uh interaction is a virtual
tables that actually enable inbound
interaction from data ver into business
Central using business Central cruit API
without duplicating without replicating
data so that's another um um interaction
that's enabled um uh through this
integration right so essentially you can
actually um you can use data syn and
virtual tables uh complementary to each
other if you have a big r only table you
don't really need to sync and copy all
the data into dataverse you can actually
just use Virtual table Sasha dataverse
can actually read that data from
business Central without duplicating
it the third interaction top is
uh what we call data cut events that
enable outburn interaction so basically
from business Central to to shout to
data ver saying like hey there's
something Chang in me so if there
whenever there's a data changes that are
being created updated or deleted
business centrer can actually trigger a
power automate flows using when a row is
added modified or deleted trigger so
that's actually um uh uh enabling the
integration uh outbound integration from
business Central into a um data ver and
finally another outline interaction is
when business Central can tell dat that
has an action perform on their data or
on anything anywhere on the on the app
itself so in this case um it's called
business event and um uh this business
event can actually trigger a power
automate flows that using a when an
action is performed trigger on data vers
site so the Improvement on those four
complimentary app interaction that come
with this release are for
example on data SNS uh I will refer you
to the the first part of the session
that was presented by my uh colleagu
Ivan colleage which is um the session is
called the same same like this session
what's new in data verse and Dynamics uh
365 app integration part one um my uh my
colleague will talk about all the
Improvement in the data synchronization
area and on the virtual tables
essentially I'd like to announce the
first uh time General availability or GA
that's coming this November for our
virtual tables and a big feature that
enabled our virtual tables which is the
preview of Po Pages support that allow
access to busy data from unlicensed user
I will talk more about it and I will
demo that uh that features right later
and Improvement on the data cut events
essentially we increase the amount of uh
event can be processed within 30 seconds
delay time it used to be 100 data change
event now we can actually process one
1,000 and um to be sent a separate
notification right these numbers the
number of notification and delay time is
actually controlled by server settings
and the server setting in Business
Center are called API subscription max
number of notification and API
subscription delay time the server
settings can actually be changed using
your own extension so if you want to
increase the number of notification or
reduce the time of delay you can
actually use um uh use your extension
tool subscribe or listen to the on get
maximum number of notification and on
get delay time events this event is
triggered when the base app of business
Central try to read that server settings
when that happen your extension can
actually intercept and um overwrite that
value the Devol value of 130 seconds
into any value you want all right and
finally on business event we have three
Improvement business event is still in
preview and we are targeting a g a in
the um in the release after this one
right now uh we actually adding Fring
Fring support when we released version
1.0 of events right now previously we
released version zero now we have
version
1.0 and we also um um introduced a
troubleshooting support that U enabled
by uh two system tables uh external
event subscription and external event
activity loog that also come with the
uip page Pages uh that's coming in um
this this November uh 20
2023 and finally we also send all those
events um to partner Telemetry to to
application Insight such that you can
actually um query uh all your the events
that generated that um um um uh from
business Central okay and that's also uh
targeted for November uh 23 so I'll show
all those demo also at the
end all right so let's talk about the
big feature that we announced for this
release which is power pag support via
virtual tables right so power pag
support of V fre tables is actually
enable access to BC data in three main
scenarios the first scenario is
anonymous access for external external
or unlicensed user without signing in so
this is the first time that we are
actually
allowing um non-licensed BC user
external user like for example a user
from your C customer or your vendors to
actually access BC data without signing
in that's the first scenario the second
scenario is like if when you allow those
user those uh external unlicensed user
to sign in so then then the scenario
become authenticated access for those
user after registration and signing in
so that's also um um a way for us to
show related relevant data to those
authenticated user that's those those
are the two new new scenarios that's
introduced with the power Pages access
the third scenario is essentially a
scenario that you already have for
example essentially a virtual table
access this is authenticated access for
internal or license user you already
internal or licensed user can only can
they can already access BC data using
power apps like model driven app or
using power automate right so now we
just extending that functionality of Rao
tables to allow internal or BC license
user to access uh BC data through Power
pages right so you might ask what is the
difference uh the the how how do you
differentiate for internal from external
users right so this is what I'm I'm
taking from the dynamic Strat 5
licensing guide essentially I'm just
highlighting all the term that are
important essentially external user are
those user that not in an employee like
relationship with your company with your
um with the company within business
Central right and those are external
users so they they don't need to be a li
licensed user and they can access busy
data through Power Pages internal user
are ently those users that actually
employee or user are providing business
processes on behalf of you or your AV
avate those user are internal user and
they actually require BC license even if
they access it from Power pages right
and there's a illustration for our
licensing guide to differentiate what is
external and internal for example in
this case you can see that external
users not supposed to perform business
processes on behalf of your
organization while um for internal users
are all license users that actually
performing business
processes and that's it so I think it's
time for demo so let's start with the
demo of the power Pages support with the
virtual tables right so we have created
a demo site which is called um well it's
called temp site right and I have open
already I have opened this um uh this
power Pages portal in here you can see
this is for example the power pages and
what I will show you is the first the
anonymous access of of external user in
this case the external user wants to see
items for sale from chronis USA uh
Incorporated right so what I allow in
this uh Power pages is actually access
to the items table for BC you can see
here if I click on items without even uh
signing in Anonymous user like myself
can start seeing what are the item for
sale from kronis USA right so that is a
Anonymous access for of external user
now I will show you authenticated access
of external user so let's say I'm
interested to buy one of these uh
product so what I need to do is I need
to register so I will do that and click
on register I'll put let's say de demo
user
4 at
life.com let me just confirm my
password okay so when I'm registering I
essentially uh creating a new entry in
the native contact table inside data
verse so this is the registration page
so I need to put my um details as a new
authenticated user external user user
for and I have to put a organic ation
name so this is essentially how I
register the name of the customer for
Kronos USA so in this case let's say the
name of the customer is demo customer
4 okay so and then I'll just
update now I'm actually logging in as a
demo user 4 and actually register a new
customer for Kronos US USA which is um
uh demo customer 4 right now not only I
can also see the uh the it table but I
can now see the sales order table you
can see that like right now I have no
sales order because I just now register
so I want to create a new order of one
of those uh item right so I'm going to
click on a new sales
order and you can see I can actually
create a new
order let me pick one of the
product let's see uh Paris guest
chair select
uh put
quantity1 uh
submit okay so now I'm submitting a
sales order you can see in the power
Pages now I have access the
authenticated um external user which is
demo user 4 have a sales order created
uh through Power Pages now I'm going to
log out and I'm going to sign in as a
third scenario which is actually a BC
business centrer admin user um that will
process that sales order and uh ship an
invoice it so I'm going to sign in as a
asure um um Microsoft entra ID right I
just click on it and I'm signing in as a
licensed BC user now I can see all the
sales order from many many customer and
uh posted sales invoice for also for
many
customer so now I'm an authenticated
internal users and you can see see here
now I see I see there sales order from
adatom from new customer 2 and also from
the demo customer 4 which is the one
that uh I newly created with um with the
power pages right so what I want to do
is now I'm going to ship an invoice this
one
okay you can see uh the the new the new
external user actually submit an order
for Paris guest chair so I'm going to
ship an invoice it as a BC uh sales te
or internal user
right and you can see if I um press F5
refresh this sales order will disappear
because it's converted into a posted
sales
invoice you see so now all I need to do
is like I need to log out and I will let
the same external user demo user for to
sign to sign in and see what happened to
his sales older and what happened uh if
they um uh if he actually receive uh
receive a a posted sales invoice so let
me sign
out and I'm going to sign in as a demo
user
4 and you can see here it end up on the
on the sales order page and the sales
order that I submitted is gone already
so all I need to do is I check on the
sales invoice and I can see that there's
a new posted sales invoice you see so
that's uh that's essentially show you
three different access scenario using
power Pages Anonymous access of external
user authenticated access of external
user and authenticated access of
internal user so let me show you how we
actually did this demo and uh there'll
be a more documentation in detail how to
you can actually achieve this first I
want to show you how we actually achieve
anonymous uh and authenticated access
for external user so I want to show you
the uh business Central page which is
the the one that has uh Microsoft entra
app
users and you can see here there are
three Microsoft entra app user created
for this scenario the first one is uh
already exist before to support uh uh
Business Center of virtual tables so
this is actually uh it actually access
BC data impersonating authenticated
internal user with BC license from data
verse so before when you access BC data
using um uh model driven app or power
automate this is the uh entra Microsoft
entra app user use to impersonate right
the the two new Microsoft entra app user
that we created is actually to to enable
uh Anonymous external user access and
for authenticated um uh uh access for
external user and you can see in here in
this in this demo when I click on this
uh
user you can see it start um um with
this user actually have an entitlement
to access BC data but has no permission
sets so admin BC admin actually have to
assign permission set for this Microsoft
enter app user to make sure that only
only relevant uh BC data are accessible
by Anonymous external user so in this
case for this demo we give a um a wide
scope of permission for example for this
Anonymous access we provide d365
Automation and d365 read so essentially
we allowing Anonymous uh user to read
all tables in BC but in practicality
when you actually use this uh feature
you probably want to narrow the scope
and create a custom permission set to
make sure that the only read relevant
relevant table right so that is the uh
Microsoft entra app user for anonymous
access and the second one is the
Microsoft entra app user for
authenticated access in this one you
want to make sure that once the uh
external user are signed in and uh they
want to uh for example post a sales
order or make some changes then you
should probably provide a read and write
access so in this case the permission is
d335 Automation and d335 business full
access obviously this is too wide scope
uh this is just for a demo purposes in
the real practicality you probably
should provide a very very narrow uh
written and right access to only a
certain relevant table for this uh uh
external user when they sign in all
right so that those are the permission
set that admin have to set up by default
none of this uh app user has any
permission set so by default it's not
enable and then uh what you need to do
also when you design the the power pages
you actually need to provide uh for
example in the pages um let me see the
setup table permission so this is on the
site uh the data ver site on the power
Pages
site and you can see the table
permission for this uh uh portal right I
will want to show you the one that for
anonymous access for example here read
all
items you can see here for a real item
is like actually it's enabling virtual
table which is uh D 365 BC item which is
a virtual table of item BC item table in
data verse and a global access mean
Anonymous user can actually access all
the the rows in this uh table but only
read and I'm actually uh assigning this
um permission to all type all three type
of user so basically Anonymous user
authenticated external user Anonymous
external user and also authenticated uh
administrator or internal user itself so
they only read only and what I want to
show you is actually access for sales
order table and the uh sales invoice
table you can see here for example in
here you can see this H see and create
orders in here I want to actually uh
provide access for um only for a certain
contacts that actually register and only
to show tables related to the customer
created by the contact and in order to
do that you you you achieve this through
a synthetic relation so we actually set
up a synthetic relation between contact
native table with sales order virtual
table I will show this is actually um um
the concept that we introduced with
virtual table where you can actually
relate native table with a virtual table
and show only relevant um uh records
from the virtual table related to the uh
rows in the native table okay so in here
there's um a relationship contact to
sales order and the same thing
uh and this is apply to only
authenticated user right and also the
same thing for invoice table so so uh
external user uh signing in they can see
the invoices posted for them and also
here we have to create a synthetic
relation between contact native table
with the saleson voice um virtual table
and how do we actually create this um
synthetic relation is first we actually
need to make sure to extend the contact
table because the native contact table
has no idea of what is a BC customer is
right so we actually what we
do in here I'll show you so essentially
on the contact table we add a new column
that we call BC customer and this new
column is populated when a new Anonymous
user registered and sign sign up in a
portal and remember when I uh when this
Anonymous demo user for uh sign up and
register it puts the organization name
right and that organization name become
a DC customer name and put into this uh
column and the way we do that is we uh
we use that using power automate so I
will show you the power automate to do
that let's see here you go add a new BC
customer from Power page contact
registration you can see here the
trigger is essentially a data cut event
it will listen to the contact table
being modified remember when I register
as an anonymous user I put the or
organization name which is a demo
customer 4 and that's actually what it
listened to right when that is triggered
what I did is like uh the first thing in
that uh in this flow is to get what is
the default company setting for virtual
tables in this case uh kronis USA so
we'll get kronis us USA in this uh in
this step and then essentially add the
new customer entered by this uh
Anonymous user into under the kronis USA
company which is adding a new busy
customer right and then after you add a
new customer you get the customer ID and
you put the ID in the column uh the new
column BC customer column of the contact
field when you do that then you can
actually build a synthetic relation
within native contact table with uh
sales order table virtual or a sales
invoice table virtual in data verse so
let's see uh uh let me just show you the
synthetic
relation for example here uh the
synthatic relation is dynamic 365 BC
contact to sales order when I click on
it you can see this synthetic relation
is connecting native contact table to
the sales order uh BC table in data
verse it using the customer key and then
you can see the mapping is a this is
basically the new column or field that I
create in the contact table related map
to the customer ID in the sales order um
uh table right so that way you you only
show say older related to that BC
customer when whenever the anonymous uh
external user sign in and the same thing
uh we do the same thing
for the sales info syntactic relation
which is the same thing here you can see
contact native to sales invoice and the
mapping is the same from BC customer
field to the customer ID in the sales
invoice table and that is for the
syntactic corelation now what I want to
show you
is
essentially remember that uh there's a
three Improvement in business events
right there is a versioning support uh
there is uh terrible shooting using
system table and UI page and then uh
partner Telemetry where we send data of
business business event subscription not
notification into into app Insight so
what I I I did is I actually
already um I already
created flow
that um will highlight this event and
actually um remember in My Demo I
created sales invoice right uh so
there's um there's two flow that
actually listen to sales invoice posted
so there's one uh sales invoice posted
notification old which is an old version
in fact actually I can just I can show
you it's actually being triggered just
now you can see 11 minutes ago 11
minutes ago when um I um Turned that
demo user for sales order into posted
sales invoice this flow is triggered and
you can see the in this one is still
using the old version of the the old
version of the of the event which has
this payload uh there's only one URL
which is the API URL but I also have
another flow that's showing um a new
payload that's showing um uh uh web
client URL that you can actually go so I
will I will go there
let me go back and this is the new one
in fact I will just show you what's the
versioning look
like so in here you can see that here uh
I listened um to sales invoice Po and
you can see this new version 1.0 right
the difference between version 1.0 and
version 0.0 is uh the payot has uh this
new web client URL where you can
actually uh open a page in the in the in
the app okay so in this one uh you can
see it's also um it's also
triggered 11 minutes ago or 13 minutes
ago right and if you click on
it you can see the payload is different
now the pilad not only has the uh API
URL but it's also have the web client
URL so if this web CLI URL you put it in
the in the uh
browser you can actually go straight
into that
invoice that invoice posted for demo
user 4 for a demo customer 4 that um uh
I did in with power Pages it's opening
the posted sales invoice table you can
see here uh PS posted sales invoice demo
customer 4 so that's a versioning uh
support for business event and then I
want to show you the system table this
is the let me just go back Let me
refresh and this is also need to be
refreshed so what I'm showing you right
now is the system tables that support
troubleshooting for business
event the first um uh table is the
external event subscription you can see
there's a six different subscription
that's been created and the latest
one is let me
see yeah just like yesterday it was for
sales invoice post this is the one that
I I created to listen to um sales
invoice posted done by the my power
Pages demo right and then in the
activity lock you can
see the several events being sent for
example in fact today uh September 26
there are three events being sended so
actually there's the first one is
actually it's an event uh sales order
release because when I actually um uh
ship an invoice an open sales order it
has to be released first before it got
um invoice so this is the sales order
release um notification and the two
notification for sales for sales invoice
posted is actually one the old version
and the other one is the new version and
this is currently still only a system
table but uh in pretty soon we'll
provide a UI page that you can actually
correlate this um uh external
subscription with the activity lock in
one U nice UI page uh that's coming in
this November and the final uh features
on this business event that I want to
show you is essentially the partner
Telemetry so in here I'm going to show
to I'm going to go to my environment I
just want to show you here the my
production environment I have put my um
connection string for my app inside in
the uh Tenon admin Center and now I'm
going to the app insight and in here I'm
going to run
the uh what you call the
query you can see yesterday I make uh
business events uh subscription is
created for sales invoice posted and
today I want to show how many events are
triggered
successfully I'm going
to uh even
rt45 I'm going to
run and there you go today 9:26 right
when I click on
this you can see here for
example see there's a sales order
release uh being um
uh let me
see and oh the the the the timing is a
UTC timing I believe and if if I put
here and you can actually see the sales
invoice posted event also here you go
the old
one and potentially the new
one yeah there you go so all the sales
invoice posted and the sales order this
event are um push into parenty where you
can quy and correlate with other datas
so that's conclude my um uh presentation
for resources you can go to Yammer uh to
provide feedback for us and you can also
um uh join the conversation through
Twitter or you can look at our
documentation submit ideas and look for
our busc office hour and that's it uh
thank you very much um I look forward to
seeing you in uh Q in session remotely
uh pretty soon and also in in person at
Direction conference thank you for your
attention
goodbye